[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right welcome everyone to the stoa
i'm peter limberg the steward of the
store still has a place for us to cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the nice edge of this very
moment and today we are very lucky
because we have derek severs here with
us
um i'll read his me in 10 second bio
he's the man waving in the very dapper
outfit right now
um he says i'm a musician producer
circus performer
entrepreneur ted speaker and book
publisher
mono maniac um i'm curious it sounds
kind of sexy
or kinky i want to find out what that
means uh introvert slow thinker
and love finding a different point of
view he's the founder and former
president of cd baby and he's the author
of anything you want
most recently helya or no and the
upcoming book
how to live so if you've been here
before you know the drill
throw questions in the chat i'll call
you and meet yourself ask it to derek uh
if you don't wanna be on youtube
uh just indicate that read on your
behalf and we'll probably just pivot the
q a
uh right away so just start throwing
them now that being said
derek how you doing today
oh here i put you immune uh there you go
[Music]
okay you can hear me now i can hear you
all right hey everybody
um by the way you know all those things
you just said about me they're actually
all past tense i
i think my my me in 10 seconds actually
says i was
oh yes entrepreneur i have been an
entrepreneur and a musician
there was a thing a couple years ago
when i realized
that most of us hold on to titles longer
than we
should because i'm not really an
entrepreneur anymore i've been calling
myself an entrepreneur but
like actually i started a company what
23 years ago
and i sold it 13 years ago and i haven't
really started a company since then i
mean i've published books but
i wasn't trying to make money from it
you know so it's like
i thought about how just because
somebody was a high school athlete
doesn't mean they could keep calling
themselves an athlete forever like at
some point that title expires
so i went to my bio and my site and i
changed it to
past tense instead of saying i am these
things i was like i was these things
right what am i now i don't know we'll
see and and
i imagine given what you just said you
don't carry a label
uh you don't hold on empty you don't
hold on to any too tightly
um but is there any that resonates with
you right now like uh
an artist of life or something jazzy
like that
by the way peter i love how mellow you
are you know how everybody it's like
when they get on a mic they're just like
okay ladies
and gentlemen all right people you know
they like kind of cheering up this
adrenaline
i like how you're just like yeah hey so
uh yeah all right title you're using now
um so uh no i think um
right now i feel like i'm only an author
or a writer whichever award doesn't
matter to me but i feel that
up until a year or two ago i thought of
myself
as a programmer and an entrepreneur
that would sometimes write what i had
learned
and share it on my blog and now i feel
like i really
really really like writing i think it's
the most interesting thing
to talk about ideas and dive into ideas
and if i make that my main
job definition then that means i have to
do more of
that and do it better i was like yeah
this is the only thing i want to do now
uh but yeah now i'm just a writer yeah
what i got from you is that what you
identify with
uh it's almost like you have to live up
to that identity and this seems like
you're using in a positive sense like
you know what i love writing
let's call myself a writer make me do it
better
yeah years ago when i was a teenager
and we used to make business cards do
you remember business cards do we still
do those anymore um
but i had a business card because i was
trying to be a freelance
musician in new york city and so at
first i just played
guitar and then i started playing bass
because it's almost the same
and then i started taking piano lessons
and really taking piano seriously so
what i did is i
i added piano to my business card so now
anybody i was meeting
would hand in my card it's like okay i'm
on the hook now
i've defined myself as also piano player
and i started getting gigs
as a pianist and so i felt like defining
myself as such meant i had to rise to
the title
yeah i like that and circle back to your
your writing practice
um i'm curious what's your ritual you
wake up first thing in the morning
uh you're just random do you have
anything i
i it's such a difference between in
theory and in practice in theory
i would love to be a ritual guy i would
love to tell you that
every morning at 7 58 i do such and such
and by 8 am that and i do this until 1.
uh in theory yes in practice no um
not at all everything is different
so uh i was like you're in a zoom room
with a bunch of like good-looking
strangers that
get horny over the word meta uh so given
this this
context any any thoughts you'd want to
share with us about yourself or in
general
um like maybe what's a lie for you at
the edge of your thinking
a lie at the end alive for you
or lie if you lie thinking that would be
a
fun one wouldn't it especially as like a
welcome question what's a lie
hold on let's see um i wonder if i could
answer both of those
um maybe they're the same answer
yeah i mean there's the
it's funny there's a public versus
private no i don't know the okay
do you mean just kind of like it was
that a a nice way of
a poetic way of saying what's on my mind
yes
pretty much i was just thinking earlier
today
about the public and private balance
um i was talking with someone else who
also has the same tendency as me which
is to feel
the need to dive in a hundred percent to
one thing
or a hundred percent into another thing
so therefore like a very black and white
approach
and she asked me um she said well what
about
having a kid like once you have a kid i
mean that kind of means you need to put
your whole career on hold
and your work life is on hold because
your kid is your top priority now so if
i said no no no no i said yeah my kid is
my top priority but
it's got to be a balance between
public and private like if if i was like
a hundred percent
private life and i did nothing in the
public that would be really
sad to me but on the other hand if i was
public life and had no private life that
would also be really sad
so no um i mean my kid's only eight
years old
so i've only been doing this for eight
years i'm no big expert but um
i really like this idea of saying and
not or to things and not thinking we
need to pick one
or the other um and each of us finding
our balance
whether you know in my case like the
public private thing it's finding like
i like for about 40 of my life to be
public and 60
private or whatever it may be and i was
thinking of the metaphor
of the country
house and city apartment meaning there's
kind of a
centuries-long tradition for those
that can afford it to have an apartment
in the city
and a house in the country so it's not
either or you don't have to ask yourself
do i want to live in the city or
do i want to live in the country for
hundreds of years people have been
doing this thing where they have a
little apartment
um in london and a house
up in gloucestershire somewhere uh
or it's the little apartment in vienna
in the house out there whatever like the
it's i'm thinking about that
metaphorically
that that's the and answer to where to
live
that you don't have to pick one or the
other that you can set up your life in
such a way
that you can have your city apartment
and your country house and say yes to
both
because you don't need to just you don't
need to deny
any aspect of your personality or your
needs
that you could say yes to them and just
find out how to make the balance
so yeah there is a uh there's something
alive at the edge of my thinking that's
not a lie
ever like what came to mind there is
like cities dichotomies that pop up
in our mind uh and then this idea of
like getting into right
relationship with them and so like the
private versus public for
example um i publicly came out really as
a stoic since covet online
came online um and i'm finding like just
like
my avatar in the spectacle if you will
you know is making me become more stoic
and virtuous in my my daily life
because people are seeing that like oh
should i live up to it so it's like the
identity piece
um and i feel like the right
relationship with private and public is
slowly coming into place right here
so do you have any any thoughts on that
yeah okay so what you just said like i
came out as a stoic
it's like there's probably some parts of
you
that disagree or not aligned
with stoicism as an ism
uh and so the this whole idea of isms
this need to subscribe
all the way in uh maybe i've just kind
of have a bad association with isms but
when i think of like
anything that ends with ism it's it's
this kind of all-in subscription
uh to something um which reminds me of
when i lived in santa monica california
for a few years
everybody in santa monica california
is into yoga and not just doing yoga not
just you know
a downward dog and doing it and enjoying
the physical thing they go
all into this whole culture of it where
everything just becomes
namaste and they all drink the same kind
of matcha thing and they all wear the
same stuff and they carry their mats
around
and now they take on this new lifestyle
where everything in their house is
suddenly bamboo
with little what is it it's just
this this needs to go all into an
identity and go
this is me now that was the old me this
is the real me this is the new me
and that's kind of an ism it's it's
buying in all the way
um whereas i think the and not
or i think can apply to this too you can
say
i like stoicism i believe in what
they're saying
i believe this is a great way to be and
i also do some things which are
completely counter to it
and i like those things too that you
don't have to pick just one
philosophy and say this is it for me you
can um
you can listen to ac dc and debussy
you don't have to pick one
yeah uh i think we're going to call
ourselves the weird stoics here because
we're doing exactly that having all
these like philosophy sex with all these
different
you know reality tunnels here um that
does resonate
um so i'm not gonna hog you anymore uh
so i'm gonna pivot to the
q a uh i've been trying not to look down
but it's funny the uh
it was a victory that said something
like oh yes i enjoy my little apartment
and my posh mansion i was like okay i
can't look down i'm going to laugh too
much but yeah
yeah the chats chess will get in trouble
um
and the title this this event was like
uh entrepreneurialism
and uh the spiritual i don't know what
it was but we don't have to talk
about that thank you for making a title
but we didn't need to
do it uh cody you are up
um thanks there's something that that's
that's it's like
really alive and like i think i wrote a
question in there mainly just to get
your attention peter because i actually
like
you two talking to each other and then
the first conversation i had with you
peter i'm like man you should get derek
on here because you said something
really awesome
that was like and you're like yeah i've
already talked to derek and i'm like all
right well perfect because he said
something really awesome when you're
thinking and you're still
i i watch you read your newsletters i
watch you think about what the stoa
is and like what you're what a steward
of the stoa is and like this
this how it's different than rebel
wisdom and this kind of gorilla punk
rock
atmosphere that this thing has and so
its identity
seems to be like alive and just what
your two are talking about this like
this identity that's like not an
identity you know it's like
it's it's playing these dualities and
and at the same time like this thing
needs to
sustain ideally sustains peter
so that we can keep having this place
and peter doesn't have to like go do
other things and we like all have to
pick up the pieces and we'll do it
poorly probably
um so where is the can you provide some
wisdom
can you give peter some wisdom and us
all some wisdom that we can support him
and also like in this world that's like
this isn't
a corporation this isn't a business but
it is
somehow trying to make a living you know
so it has its own like identity crisis
um
how do we it's doing well it's doing
well
is it peter is it going all right peter
adds some more interiors
he's going all right yeah all right all
right
all right it's not good enough well no i
mean
okay the real question was is it
sustainable
as it is now um
yeah it's a big question because we've
only been around for um
seven months really and about uh 200
people are supporting on patreon and
that's increasing
i'm not really thinking about livelihood
too much
but i think it will eventually go there
uh
yeah i think cody's asking how to make
it kind of like
maybe interface with the community more
make it more alive and keep growing
without getting burnt out and you know
um what not yeah that's probably
there's um i wish i was that kind of
business mind like
seth godin man if you ever see that guy
live in action
um his his ideas
are instant i went to like a town hall
thing in new york city with him
where strangers would stand up and say
uh
i've got this idea for a dog food
business but i don't know what to do
what do you think i should do
without missing a beef he's like here's
what you need to do
and it was just like it was breathtaking
it was like that's a great idea oh my
god that was off the top of his head
and the next person would stand up and
ask a question about something
completely different and he'd say
yeah here's an idea and again i was like
[ __ ] that was brilliant
oh my god he's doing that live it was
like watching a master jazz improviser
right like
like maybe i could play a solo that
brilliant
but with much you know composition and
thought but
for the brilliant improviser just does
that live so sorry i'm
not that kind of business mind that
could come up
with a great idea for peter right now
sorry yeah no no no i don't i don't
think
i don't think it's so much that you know
what uh that that is needed there's
something i remember reading um were you
speaking about
when you were doing cd baby and sorry
this is going into entrepreneurial but i
think you do this in your own life
of uh where you tried to do something
but people didn't want that
that's not what people wanted you were
and so there was this aspect of
listening to
people and i think there's a balance
there of like having an idea
then also listening to actually what
people want and what people are telling
you to do
and like there's a balance there too and
so like maybe i just want to keep
harking on this like
man it's hard to have one identity when
there's this other whole
opposite side and how you do that in the
daily life and really maintain that
balance without just like
toppling over in this day right well it
helps to know okay so
a music teacher when i was a teenager
told me something that
that i found interesting he felt it was
crucial he said like this is the most
important thing you need to know
he said before you go out into the music
business you need to know
what approach you're taking are you
going to please the industry
or are you going to please yourself and
i said well both
and he said no you need to pick you need
to choose
like ultimately it's going to come down
to that if
you know this or that decision um
he said because if you're going to
please the industry you can study
the billboard top hits and you can
figure out how to make
a hit and you can figure out how to get
rich
or you can decide that that ultimately
doesn't matter that much to you and
you're going to just make the music
you want to make and if it makes some
money that's fine
if it's able to support you and pay for
your cost of living
that's great and if anything more than
that is just dessert
so it depends on peter's
intentions too like um he may feel like
you know what
it may even be that the stoa loses money
each month but he says you know what i
this is worth it to me like some people
have a hobby where they spend money on
bicycles and
go on bike trips some people buy ping
pong tables i'm
spending my time and money on the stowa
because i enjoy doing this
even if it loses money um so yeah it
depends
with intentions too like there are uh
yeah
all of us have things that we do not for
the money
and we just choose that this is what we
like doing not every i actually
kind of hate the monetization of
everything
i hate that um that every good idea
needs to
immediately have this like okay how can
we monetize this
um and i i resist that a lot by keeping
things
super like diy technically like when you
go to my website
it's like s-i-v-e dot rs it's just this
bare-bones static html
because i'm like no i'm not going to go
into that hole of filling it with
javascript and stuff that's going to
make it expensive to run and i don't
have employees and
all of that because then i'd have to ask
the question of how to monetize this
um but yeah so maybe i don't know peter
if you're feeling the same way about the
stoic like you're just gonna do this no
matter what
yeah one thing uh i recall reading your
book i read it years ago
but i got a sense um it's like you're
just doing it for fun number one and
then
anytime something came to you like some
[ __ ] hit the fan you use that as a
forcing function to create some policies
or whatever
and it's not like you have this top down
thing going on and i also got a sense
that like
you could end at any time and be cool
with it mm-hmm
yeah literally um i did i
i had some weird paranoid fear i can
tell you guys now the old cd baby logo
uh the original cd baby logo i had
actually scanned it off of a hallmark
card
because it was just something i was just
doing in my living room so
there was a funny picture of a baby face
going like that on a hallmark card so i
scanned the hallmark card and i put it
inside i photoshopped it with layering
into
the whole of my cd and that was the logo
so i was always scared that
hallmark was going to find this out and
sue my ass to the ground
and so it kind of felt like at any point
this whole thing could shut down and i
had to always be okay with that
um yeah we all know this does have some
comparison there we don't need to say
that blatantly yeah
i was trying to fish for it but
i don't want to be obvious um all right
jess you had some questions
i have a bunch of questions but i'll
just pick the last one that i wrote
um which is uh you've talked a bunch
about this
um kind of refusing to choose
philosophy um and that's something i
really admire because um like
uh i've been trying to do that in my own
life like i
um quit a job last year and was trying
been trying to build something new and
it's basically been like this refusing
to pick
any one thing a friend said something i
asked her what she was gonna do and she
said i'm gonna live well
every day for the rest of my life and
i guess the question is like how do you
if that's the way that you live
first of all i guess is there a way that
that connects to your
spiritual self spiritual practice or
anything and also how do you know if
you're like
like moment by moment or day by day like
how do you know if you're kind of going
wildly off base
in relation to that like how do you know
if you're accidentally falling into some
trap
and what kinds of like traps are they um
um i'm gonna answer sideways there's a
interesting quote i heard recently which
is um
an open mind like an open mouth
needs to eventually close on something
and when i heard that i went oh god
that's good because like sometimes i
am too open-minded which then made me
kind of reflect on what does that mean
too open-minded it's like well you're
too open-minded when you never decide
on anything when you just are always
leaving all options open
um you can do that to a fault and i
really like that thing we do in english
where you could say like any positive
thing and you can say to a fault
somebody can be generous to a fault um
sweet to a fault and open-minded to a
fault
which means always open never deciding
um and i heard that the the latin root
of the word decide
i think the dec in there means cut to
like to cut off other options
we need to decide things so um so i
think that
this idea of i'm always just going to do
whatever i want
um it could be a rationalization
for not deciding something um
and i guess you don't nobody ever needs
to decide anything until you find out
that it's actually getting in the way of
what you
want most so i often think about this
dichotomy but like what you want
now versus what you want most like what
i want
now is chocolate all the time what i
want most is to be healthy
uh so if i only were to observe the now
and have chocolate all the time
it would uh it would hurt what i want
most
and you know there's always a
metaphorical version of that like
it's fun to just do what we want every
day but that's kind of a shallow happy
and sometimes the deeper rewards come
from
not following your daily impulses and
doing what you want
most um that's how i think of it there
are lots of things i do
in a day that i don't really want to do
today but i know that that's what i want
most
does that make sense or does that help i
think i kind of answered that
yeah i guess um it's also not so much
about like whether or not you follow
like any given
impulse but also like whether
or how you make sure to include all of
the aspects of yourself in a full life
like all of that that's kind of the
thing i'm
i'm referring to like like for me it's
like right now i don't have a guitar
and there's some part of me that isn't
really awake because the guitar is on
the wrong side of the country
you know or that's that's a very literal
expression no that's great
i got as you can tell i like those
little metaphors um
uh it's funny i'm
okay you guys are you know i'm not here
to promote anything
so please don't think that i'm saying
this for any self-promotional reason but
i'm
i'm still writing my next book called
how to live
and uh it's totally up your alley you
plural everybody with top row because uh
it's the um
the whole the idea it's so much fun
sorry if you don't mind i'm going to
pause
you'll see it has to come full circle of
what you're just saying there's a book
called sum by david eagleman uh
some spelled s-u-m and it's probably my
single favorite book of all time because
i think the format is so brilliant
because it's 40 little short stories the
subtitle is uh 40 tales from the
afterlives
and every little short story uh
answers the question of what happens
when you die wait cody did you just hold
it up
just so um
every little short story inside every
chapter answers what happens when you
die
but every chapter disagrees with all of
the others
so it's like chapter three here's what
happens when you die you're awake and
you're surrounded by these little
creatures
chapter four when you die you're in a
giant empty
mansion and nobody's there and you walk
for days chapters nine
when you die uh you're immediately
accosted but yeah
so i love this format of
answering the same question a bunch of
times
in deliberately conflicting ways and i
read the book twice
over two years and then suddenly while
driving down the road i went
i want to write a book called how to
live that's going to steal his format
it every chapter is going to be
completely convinced
that it has the answer on how to live
and it's going to say here's how to live
uh freedom
freedom is how to live that all misery
comes from
um attachments that you don't want we
always need to be free and independent
at all times
and here is how to do it here's a recipe
for the most independent free life
and this is how you should live uh next
chapter
here's how to live commit all great
things in life
come from committing from the deeper
happiness of being rooted committing to
a person committing to the mastery path
of a
of a career committing to a place
committing to people
and each chapter is completely convinced
that it has
the right answer um it's a blast to
write
so with that said my full circle is that
uh
last week i was just writing the balance
chapter
it was like here's how to live balance
like
look at look at the balance of nature
the balance of this like all
um all these adjectives about when
somebody's crazy we say that they're
imbalanced or that they're
off balance or that they're um uh
you know all happiness all the good life
is a balanced life
but so in the concrete how to live
this way it was about using the clock
as your ally like a hunter uses his
hunting dog
to let the clock um aid you in your
balance
because if we just let our
desires run their course then we end up
doing too much of what makes us happy
um we do not enough of the things that
we need to do but
don't make us happy in the moment and so
therefore
if you acknowledge these different
aspects of your personality
that need to be balanced your different
needs uh public versus private your need
everybody has a human need for certainty
but we all have a human need for
uncertainty
and those are clashing things but you
need to acknowledge both of them
and what most people do is they swing
their lives in this pendulum
where they follow one path for a few
years and they say hey man i'm just i'm
gonna
quit my job and go completely nomadic
and it's because they've had too much
certainty in their life
no offense and um so they so they go
all the way the other side because they
say i've been ignoring this aspect of my
personality so they go 100
to this other one but now they're
imbalanced again now there's like too
much uncertainty and after a couple
years they go i just need a little more
root in this
so instead the balance chapter is uh
saying that you have to use the clock to
acknowledge um the clock on the calendar
to schedule your
need for uncertainty your needs for
certainty
your needs to make music you need to
learn you need to create and express
yourself
[Music]
yeah that's how my balance chapter would
answer that
awesome thank you jess
victor you had some plus ones if you can
unmute yourself and ask your question
victor
maybe he disappeared um okay i see
victor but i can't hear him
um asked to unmute you you go
okay yeah there you go oh okay cool hey
derek
hi yeah i was intrigued by the uh um
the title of this session and so i
thought oh just ask the direct and easy
question which is like
tell us in what way you see
entrepreneurialism as a spiritual
practice
because um that landed really strong
with me
and i'm interested to hear your take
oh uh let me try to make up a take then
um let me think
do i i don't know um
i never you know i i only recently
realized that
the word spiritual has the word spirit
in there which seems to imply that like
some
some ghosty thing um and so i
now i'm suddenly like unsure if i
ever knew what that word meant i also
just
yesterday i found out the definition of
the word pithy i've been called pithy
for years and i i with pith i think of
the inside of
wood and it's just like this really
lightweight thing and so every time
somebody
called me pithy i thought they kind of
meant i was an airhead
i thought oh okay sure i could summon
airhead if everybody says so
and then just yesterday i looked it up
and it said you know like powerful and
profound it went
oh uh so now i don't know spiritual
i'm not sure if i know what that means
but um
entrepreneurism or entrepreneurship and
spiritualism um
yeah sorry i don't know if you if
there's a variation on that question if
you want to ask
a slightly different angle that i might
be able to
say something about if you want
ah now i'm beginning to wonder if like i
made up the title
no i think i also saw that just before
it's not your fault
no okay well then it's like it's my
fault technically
i'm gonna i'll i'll try out a practice
here which is like the
the collective uh presencing practice
where i sit with something for just a
second get uncomfortable and spit out
whatever comes
so what's it like
coming into a space that you're
unfamiliar with
and uncertain about what expectations
might
pre-exist your arrival ooh
it you have to have this
confidence that you can do this um
yeah that's there's like a deep i'm
thinking about this with parenting
because my kid is eight and how to
instill
this feeling of like i can handle this
no matter what happens you know
terrible things happen uh i can handle
this
uh i'm entering into something i've
never done before i can handle this
um somebody i love just died i can
handle this
um thinking of like what i feel like i'm
i need a
um almost like a little mantra there
that i could help instill into his head
um it's a funny thing like having a kid
and
um thinking of how you can influence
them so ever since he was born
i sing him lullabies every night and one
time when he was um
about three years old um
i was singing the usual lullabies i
would sing in blackbird and hey jude and
over the rainbow
and yesterday so it's like some beetles
just things i felt like had a nice
singing melody
and i thought wait a minute i'm a
songwriter i've written over 100 songs
i can put an idea into his head like
let me sing let me think put things into
his subconscious
so i made up a song for him one night
that went uh
whatever scares you go do it
whatever scares you go do it because
then you won't be
scared anymore won't be scared anymore
won't be scared anymore
until you are then whatever
scares you go do it whatever you know
repeat repeat
um and i've been doing that since he was
two so now
whenever we're out and playing and he's
about to you know
climb up the tree really high and he
goes i'm scared and i always go
whatever scares you and he goes go do it
it's like yeah that's in there now
um so yeah entering into something you
entering into something completely
unknown
um i might have an answer to your
entrepreneur
question now a minute later um
i think i think of
entrepreneurship differently than a lot
of people seem to because
um i wasn't trying to be an entrepreneur
um people started calling me that later
i was
really to me it was like a charitable
thing i was doing
um i mean again sorry i'm not pushing
books but i
in my book called anything you want um
about like how i started my company
um i didn't realize till other people
told me so
but um the whole way that i was
approaching it
was like i had already made a good
living as a musician like i was already
i already
bought a house in woodstock with the
money i made touring like
by my own definition i was already
successful
and so then i built this little web
store to sell my cd i just did this for
myself
but then my friends in new york city
that were musicians
started asking me like hey man could you
sell my cd through your thing
so as a favor to my friends i started
selling their cd
and i took no money for doing it it was
just like i just did it as a favor
and then friends of friends and then
strangers started calling it's like
weren't even a friend of a friend they
just heard of it from someone and they
started sending me their music
so i i picked a price like i set an
amount that would just kind of pay for
my time
but i still thought that of this like as
my community service
um like the world has been good to me
it's time i give something back and
yeah i was just doing this the way that
some people would volunteer at a soup
kitchen or something
and then it got really popular and
became a full-time job and i had to hire
somebody to help me do it and so on
um so the whole time i never thought of
it as like
that narrative that people put around
this thing like
how'd you get the confidence to quit
your job and start a business and
believe in your dreams i'm like
none of that none of that applied i just
i was just helping my friends
so i do think there's something to that
though of
putting yourself out into the world
um to offer your help to like just be a
public servant
and help what people seem to need help
with
um whether that's a service or a product
or something that people need help with
you just
you're there to help and i think if you
switch your focus
from how can i make money me me me me
you flip that and say all right this is
forget me i don't care about me
how can i help you guys what's up what
what do you need
um that doing that switch of mindset
seems to be very rewarding like the
world rewards you
for switching that so if you want to
call that kind of spiritual maybe
cool um and if you don't mind derek if i
can use that lullaby for the next intro
music for the next event uh
i would appreciate that someone in the
chat says uh
we should have a meta modern lullaby
still album so maybe
yes oh you know what hey wait you guys
are the
the best audience one of my like little
whimsical ideas i had once it's like oh
man
i i got kind of close to thinking we
should really do this um
what do you guys think of uh
of this idea that that if somebody's
jewish
they can go if they need some wisdom
they go talk to their rabbi
right if somebody's catholic i guess
they can go
into the confession box and talk to the
priest it's not just for confession you
can like
get wisdom from the the wise elder but
those of us that like stoicism we don't
have like
a sage that we can turn to right so what
if
we make uh like stoic sage
um as a as a service like almost like a
num a phone number you could call
and it doesn't necessarily mean that
that
it needs to be one brilliant genius on
the receiving end it could be
like all of us um
like collectively kind of being your
highest self and and
channeling the the best wisdom you've
heard
um because even when i years ago like 16
years ago i hired a
like a life coach type person um and
i only found out later that this dude
was like younger than me
and had had no particular success in
life but he was a great coach for me
because when i would call him with a
problem
he would just channel the wisdom that he
had read through books he was basically
just kind of echoing
what he heard through books but by being
a little bit separated from it he didn't
know me
we'd never even seen each other he was
just a phone call i would make
um i would tell him what was up a
problem i was wrestling with and he'd
say
hmm what about this and he'd give her an
approach that was just something he had
heard
so i thought of yeah stoic sage as a
service a wisdom hotline whether it's an
email address or a phone call or a
live chat when you're feeling stuck with
something you want to know what the
stoic sage would say
we can all channel our stoic wisdom yeah
i love it
it's sort of like the the collective
part like the next buddha is the sangha
or like a decentralized psychotherapy
you know someone comes in and all this
metastoics just kind of
give them love and wisdom i like it
so yeah i love the wise too we'll make
up a stoic lullaby album to put
healthy thoughts into the next
generation's heads
um all right pranab
you're up next cool
um i have two questions which one should
i pick
yeah i guess on your about page you have
a list of
all these different kind of traits and
um
behaviors that you kind of prefer that
are kind of against the norm or against
what
people typically think of as accepted uh
i guess how did you kind of decide on
those and
how long did it take you to really
accept those things part of your as a
part of yourself um
were there some things that were more
difficult to accept than others and kind
of how did you
what was your process like to you know
find yourself i guess
decades of pain and shame um
no that's seriously that you're looking
at like i'm 51 now that's like decades
of slowly admitting
my tastes and preferences and catching a
lot of [ __ ] for it and
people getting mad about it and
me either realizing i was in the wrong
or saying no it's just
i see i i seem to just want something
that's different from what most people
want
um and the about page was actually a bit
of like an
outing of myself peter you used that
word earlier um
i outed myself in many ways especially
like the most
despicable one in there that i'm still
okay with is that i'm not into my family
like i don't love my parents
um and when people hear that they think
oh
something's wrong with you you need to
go see a shrink i'm like i don't know it
took decades before just saying no
nothing's wrong with me i just um i just
don't love my parents and i never did
not even as a little kid i just don't
feel any connection with them
and since putting that out into the
world i've heard
from some other people uh that feel the
same way
and it's so liberating for them to read
that like oh my god you two
like and you know they reach out and say
god it's so nice to talk to somebody
that feels this way because all my
friends give me so much [ __ ] for not
loving my family and
tell me something's wrong with me but um
uh by the way when i say my family i
mean like my
parents not like my kid i love my kid
but if someday my kid says he doesn't
love me then
i would get it um so yeah so sorry i
think it's just been like
you know decades on earth and like
slowly admitting things that are
seem to be here to stay that are just my
tendencies um
which you know it doesn't mean they're
unchangeable in fact lots of things
change but i guess we all have our
that's the nature and nurture balance
right we have our nature
and then sometimes nurture can change
your nature
it's kind of what cognitive behavioral
therapy is about like kind of
rational thoughts can actually change
the irrational emotions underneath them
sometimes um yeah
anyway tangent sorry did that help that
was cool thanks
all right uh katrina you had some
questions
yes hi everyone um first eric thank you
so much for
the very sweet lullaby i the moment i
heard i was like i can go do anything i
want right now i feel so
like hippie-backed by this um so i love
that you did that for us thank you
um so the the context of the questions
that i'm asking
um is basically like i'm 26 right now
and
uh in your 20s you seek to find yourself
and i did something recently where i
hired a coach for myself and you'd
mentioned that you hired a coach for
yourself too and that's what inspired
this question and i remember um
in making that decision there was some
shame in it like i should know how to do
what i want to do i read all the books i
follow
all the blogs like there's this wealth
of productivity information on the
internet like why am i getting stuck
um and then finally i was like i just
need help um
so in hiring a coach and also finding
really wonderful communities on the
internet like these
really great student communities i feel
like that has been the shifting point
for me
in getting out of my own head um so i
guess i would i really would love to
hear if there are any particular stories
in your life
um in which uh well the specific
question was what has been one of the
most important ways that you've asked
for help from others
um and or uh what are some of the
most impactful communities that you've
been part of that have helped
you in life cool um
well i think what we're doing here is
amazing
um i don't think i'm
any smarter than anybody here i just
think it's
i'm flattered that you guys asked me to
be in the
the answer role but i would before peter
and i like
unmuted and went public i was telling
him that i'm psyched to be here because
honestly i would be the
i love this community so much and what
you guys are doing that i'd be happy to
just be on
that other end i'm pointing to my camera
to get behind it
um but okay so the asking help thing
okay so the
the idea that i said earlier about the
like stoic sage as a service
um the idea that any of us could do that
because the most helpful thing
is to get the opinion of somebody who's
not
in your head because in your head it is
like a
giant tangle of
billions of little thoughts and
considerations that are going into any
given decision you're trying to make or
what should i do it's like mixed in with
a billion things right
but then when you first the act of
having to turn it into a question i'm
like making it smaller here
that like to turn this jumble of stuff
into a question
that you ask of somebody else just that
process
is huge hugely helpful
um to say like okay if i had to describe
this to somebody else
what's the actual question so um
computer programmers do this thing
sometimes it's called rubber ducking
if you search the web you could probably
read a description of more thoughts on
it so rubber
ducking was called that because um a
couple
famous programmers said that they
actually put a rubber duck
on their monitor on their computer
monitor so when they get stuck
they have to explain it to the rubber
duck all right ducky
here's the problem i don't know how to
get and in just the act of having to
describe it
even to a rubber duck helps but now
being on the receiving end of that um
it's always easier to give advice to
your
to somebody else than it is to take it
yourself
right so um
if all those things that big jumble of
things in your head
that's making you feel lost and confused
if you were somebody else
asking yourself that question it would
be easy for you to give that person
advice you'd say what to do because
you're not in
that jumble of thoughts it's easier to
see
what somebody else should be doing um
when you're not in there in the mess of
tangled thoughts so um
yeah i think that asking almost anybody
for help or for feedback especially
someone that doesn't know you well
that's what i really like about this
idea about the rabbi um
even years ago before i'd heard of
stoicism i always liked that idea of
like
because i lived in new york city for
years and i you know there were like
these like jewish communities
i i had a clear picture of the rabbi
that i would go to for wisdom um
so whenever i get stuck i'd often think
like what would the rabbi say
and so there's like this little rabbi in
my head that is
basically busy and disinterested and
just like all right
yeah i'll give you two minutes what's
the problem i might have to like
tell him my problem in two minutes i
don't have time for the details what
what is it
uh and i have to reduce it down to that
and of course if you reduce the problem
down to two minutes
and you think of like what would the
rabbi say you know we can even do that
in our heads but
having another person do that is great
so um when somebody asks my advice on
like
finding a great mentor or a great life
coach
i say no you don't need to find a great
one just any of them
any of those people that are out there
calling themselves a life coach
don't uh don't hate the fact that
they're just a uh
25 year old on a beach in bali that's
just looking to make some money by
calling themselves a life coach
sometimes even that can be useful you
know just telling your problem
to a 25 year old on a beach in bali
that's calling themselves a life coach
can be useful they don't have to be
um a super sage themselves just
describing it to somebody else
and and even if you disagree with what
they say so sometimes this guy that i
hired 16 years ago
um and i found him just through tony
robbins company
right like i love tony robbins books i
did back then um
so i went to i clicked coaching it said
you know
request coaching i signed up and they
assigned me to some guy
um and it was super useful um
so yeah doesn't even have to be somebody
brilliant so
yeah i think yeah remove the stigmas
about asking for help is a bad thing i
think we should
make it more popular to we should all be
asking somebody outside of our own head
for help
cool thank you sure all right so
this might be the last question because
we do have to end at the hour
um okay
engine you're up
derek i think the most played youtube
video after rihanna umbrella
is your leadership lessons from uh
dancing guy
uh for me um i've come back to that
year after year and it's often what i
show to people and
it kind of blew my mind um for
for um for those in the audience derek
is narrating this video at a music
festival
where this low nut is dancing um and
before you know it by the end of the
video there's an enti
everybody is dancing with them and he's
made a movement um and
derek i'm just curious you had this
fantastic takeaway that
leadership is over glorified if you
watch the video it was the first
follower
that was the most important to turning
the lone nut into a movement
i'm curious how this principle has like
been a part of your thinking and played
out in your life since you've made that
video
and if you change your mind about any
aspects of it
i'm so sorry to have a non-answer for
that
fun question especially if it's the last
question but
no um i basically have almost
no thoughts on leadership uh it was
it was a youtube video that was bouncing
around the web it was like on reddit or
something in 2009
i watched it and i went huh huh and then
like a little later i was like
huh that's kind of like that was kind of
like a metaphor for leadership wasn't it
i think i had just recently read malcolm
gladwell's tipping point and i had just
read seth godin's book called tribes
and um i have no thoughts on leadership
of my own
i was only channeling what i had read in
the tipping point in tribes and i went
huh i get what's happening here it's
like because one guy did it but like
really he was just on his own but once
somebody started following him
that's what made other people get up and
following but now look people came in
slowly and once there were like three or
four people
now the people that were standing on the
fence feel okay about getting in
so i only had basically three minutes of
stuff to say about that and i wrote a
little tiny blog post
and then the ted conference put out a
call for speakers and i tossed my hat in
the ring and they chose that
and um i did it on stage at ted
and i was nervous as hell and
after i did that talk um which sorry
this sounds like i'm
um bragging but uh
it got a standing ovation at ted which
is weird that only happens about like
once a day at ted that they
everybody stands up for a speaker so i
was the guy that day and it was really
flattering
so after i gave the talk for the next
three days all of these
like literary agents came up to me going
oh my god you need to turn this into a
book and you know i wanna
you know we're gonna i can get you onto
the speaking circuit to talk about your
leadership lessons we need to make a
book out of this and i just kind of said
no to all of them i said
i have nothing more to say that was it i
had a three minutes worth of
a metaphor to make and that's all i have
to say about that so i said no to all of
them
so sorry um i don't actually think about
it much
it was something i did once in 2009 for
three minutes and that was that
um but i know you guys have to go
on the hour uh peter told me to dance
but this is like the uh
i gotta tell you guys this is like the
coolest conversation
i've had in a long time and i [ __ ]
love these questions
and uh i kind of wish we could do this
for like two more hours
um so peter maybe we'll do a
part two soon um uh
and in the meantime uh i'm actually kind
of scared i see that the little chat
thing down below says 99 plus like they
were 99 queued up
questions so um another idea is
you know my email address is just derek
sivers.org
and i actually put aside time every day
to answer every email
um so please uh if you had leftover
questions you didn't get the chance to
do here in the whole group
um please email me it's actually a lot
of my blog posts
publicly have come from people's
questions so um
yeah it might even turn into a public
thing um yeah email me
anybody that didn't get the chance to
ask your question here uh
yeah we can do one more if we got five
more minutes
um yeah maybe i'll sneak one in uh
myself um the
you know there's something like uh
deliciously original about you like
you're you
um and i got that sense when i read your
book get the sense now
and i'm wondering if there was a
consistent like
maybe call it energy or maybe like a
principles that surround that energy
when you're an entrepreneur and like
what you're doing now
or did your kind of like philosophy or
world views or principles
change with this change of life
no definitely um it's it's hard to
figure out why
you are the way you are but um i think
it's just because
um when i was a little kid we moved
around a lot
so um when i was five years old we moved
i was
like went to a hippie school in
california when i was five we moved to
england
for a year and everybody called me the
american kid and i just felt like
oh you hate you english people i don't
like the way you do things
your rules don't apply to me but then i
moved back to america
and everybody called me the english kid
because i'd picked up the accent
and so now i didn't feel a part of
america i didn't feel part of england
and then i went to like a uh kind of a
posh high school but i just wanted to be
a heavy metal musician
so everything that my uh posh high
school friends were doing trying to get
into ivy league schools i felt like none
of this applies to me i'm just gonna be
a musician
um but then as a musician i felt like i
didn't want to be
like my other musician friends i wanted
to do my own thing so i think i
it's probably just a long history of
feeling
like um okay the thing that you guys are
after is not what i'm after i'm just
doing a different thing
um so it had nothing to do with the
entrepreneur
thing that came later um i think this
whole approach to life just kind of
feels like
um not a part of the game that everybody
else seems to be
subscribing to but at the same time not
feeling that
um i don't think i'm that
unique uh i just think of myself as
pretty normal but everybody else says
i'm weird
well whatever you are i think we all
vibe with you so i think that is uh
me too i love this i love these
questions i really mean like
i know that's not like a kind of a
[ __ ] flattery thing like hey guys
wish i could stay all night gotta go
but no i actually this is uh the best
conversation i've had in a long time so
i'd be happy to come back anytime and i
love these questions and i love this
subject of conversation so yeah
everybody please email me
uh your question if i didn't get to it
and uh
yeah have me back whenever you want i'm
happy to join beautiful uh so i'll
circle back with an email set something
up everyone's like saying bring them
back here and back
someone even privately messaged me so
the consensus is that
derek is distractibly uh distractingly
attractive and i said i said i agree
thank you all right so
here here we'll end with this i'm
looking out i showed peter
i'm at the top of the hill in wellington
new zealand so the whole time we've been
talking i'm like looking out
the glistening ocean so there's there's
distractingly attractive for me
it's wellington new zealand it's so nice
to be here um
anyway sorry thanks again for having me
yeah we're all gonna
come like invade new zealand on boats i
think after he told me that there's like
no covet thing going on there
yeah it's 2019 here yeah sorry jess life
is hard yes
all right so um we'll plug the
announcement at the event that's coming
up right now
it's uh you might like this effect erica
the dawn of the meta tribe with tyler
alterman
um so there's this sound like we have a
kinetic tribe people around us in the
meta tribe or like people we find on the
internet like find the others on places
like the stone and whatnot
so that's coming up um and and maybe
jess you want to plug your social design
club real real brief on wednesdays
yes i do um so tomorrow
at uh 1 30 pst
so 1 30 est which is 10 30
uh pst sorry i'm time zone challenge
right now uh it's on the store website
we have the social design club um if you
haven't been before
uh it's where people who are practicing
the craft of social design come together
to
learn from different systems and to
pull designs apart and try and make them
better we have a new format where a
presenter comes and we
give them a bunch of experts give
critiques and then the audience tries to
beat the experts and give better
critiques uh tomorrow we actually have
someone who has been
working on a game from but i think he
did in the media
mediators uh session uh which
is uh kind of about steel manning if
you're familiar with that taking
and arguing for the position that's the
opposite of your political position
uh so if you're interested in coming and
giving critiques
or watching the critiques happen as well
um that's on tomorrow
at 1 30 uh est
beautiful uh all right so we've got to
close this up there's still a website
the chats the patreon and then the sub
stack
uh derek everyone mwah thank you so much
for coming to stillwater today thanks
for having me
you again i hope